<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE book-review PUBLIC "-//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.2.0//EN//XML" "art520.dtd" []>
<book-review version="5.2" xml:lang="en" docsubtype="brv">
	<item-info>
		<jid>ANIFEE</jid>
		<aid>13209</aid>
		<ce:pii>S0377-8401(14)00409-X</ce:pii>
		<ce:doi>10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2014.12.008</ce:doi>
		<ce:copyright type="full-transfer" year="2014">Elsevier B.V.</ce:copyright>
	</item-info>
	<book-review-head>
		<ce:dochead id="doh0005">
			<ce:textfn>Book review</ce:textfn>
		</ce:dochead>
		<ce:other-ref id="oref1a">
			<ce:textref>Handbook
				on the Toxicology of Metals, G.F. Nordberg, B.A. Fowler, M. Nordberg
				(Eds.), Fourth ed., Volume I: General Considerations, Volume II:
				Specific Metals Academic Press as an imprint of Elsevier, Amsterdam
				(2015). 1385 pp., Hardcover, Price: 358.93 USD; 290.00 &z.euro;;
				229.53 GBP; ISBN: 978-0-444-594532-2 (Set); 978-0-12-388292-6 (Vol.
				I) (print); 978-0-12-398293-2 (Vol. II)
			</ce:textref>
		</ce:other-ref>
		<ce:author-group id="aug0005">
			<ce:author id="aut0005">
				<ce:given-name>Gerhard</ce:given-name>
				<ce:surname>Flachowsky</ce:surname>
				<ce:cross-ref id="crf0005" refid="cor0005">
					<ce:sup>&#x204e;</ce:sup>
				</ce:cross-ref>
				<ce:e-address id="eadd0005" type="email">gerhard.flachowsky@fli.bund.de</ce:e-address>
			</ce:author>
			<ce:affiliation id="aff0005">
				<ce:textfn>
					Institute of Animal Nutrition, Friedrich-Loeffler-Institute (FLI),
					Federal Research Institute of Animal Health, Bundesallee 50,
					D-38116 <!--<city> -->
					Braunschweig<!--</city> -->
					, <!--<country> -->
					Germany<!--</country> -->
				</ce:textfn>
				<sa:affiliation>
					<sa:organization>Institute of Animal Nutrition,
						Friedrich-Loeffler-Institute (FLI), Federal Research Institute of
						Animal Health</sa:organization>
					<sa:address-line>Bundesallee 50</sa:address-line>
					<sa:city>Braunschweig</sa:city>
					<sa:postal-code>D-38116</sa:postal-code>
					<sa:country>Germany</sa:country>
				</sa:affiliation>
			</ce:affiliation>
			<ce:correspondence id="cor0005">
				<ce:label>&#x204e;</ce:label>
				<ce:text>Tel.: +49 531 514112; fax: +49 531 58044 299.</ce:text>
			</ce:correspondence>
		</ce:author-group>
	</book-review-head>
	<body>
		<ce:sections>
			<ce:para id="par0005">
				Feed and food safety is one of the key elements of the present food
				and nutrition policy. Minerals such as heavy elements and toxic
				elements (
				<ce:italic>e.g.</ce:italic>
				, arsenic, cadmium, lead, mercury) and excesses of essential
				minerals (
				<ce:italic>e.g.</ce:italic>
				, copper, iodine, zinc) can contribute to feed and food unsafety.
			</ce:para>
			<ce:para id="par0010">The &ldquo;
				<ce:italic>Handbook on the Toxicology of Metals</ce:italic>&rdquo;
				is the leading book dealing with the toxicology of metals. The first
				edition of the Handbook was published in 1979, followed by the
				second edition in 1986 and the third edition in 2007. The book
				became a standard reference work for toxicologists, physicians,
				engineers and other people working in the fields of human, animal,
				environmental and occupational health.
			</ce:para>
			<ce:para id="par0015">There
				was a short interim period between the publishing of the 3rd, and
				4th editions (2007 until 2015). The reasons for this were activities
				of the Scientific Committee on the Toxicology of Metals under the
				International Commission on Occupational Health. A wealth of new
				data has appeared and therefore several chapters were completely
				rewritten and 14 new chapters were introduced in the book. In
				consequence, the fourth edition is published in two volumes &ndash;
				(I) General Considerations (25 chapters) and (II) Specific Metals
				(36 chapters). The new chapters deal with specific topics, such as
				issues of metal toxicology in developing countries; metals in food;
				the toxicology of metal and metal oxide nanoparticles; the toxic
				potential of metals released from medical devices; gene&ndash;environmental
				interactions; neurotoxicology of metals; cardiovascular disease;
				renal effects of exposure to metals, and also deals with metals of
				increasing concern such as Gold, Iridium, Lanthanum, Lithium and
				Rhodium.
			</ce:para>
			<ce:para id="par0020">In
				addition to these new chapters, all chapters from the third edition
				of the book have been updated to provide a state of the science
				perspective on a number of major public health issues. The
				increasing use of biomarkers in health has made it essential to
				update and expand the chapter on &ldquo;Biological
				monitoring and biomarkers&rdquo;. &ldquo;Exposure
				assessment, forward and reverse dosimetry&rdquo;
				has also been added to provide information on how data generated
				from biological monitoring and biomarker studies may be translated
				for risk assessment purposes through computer modeling techniques.
				Furthermore, immunotoxicology is also an expanding field; therefore
				the chapter on &ldquo;Immunotoxicology
				of metals&rdquo;
				has been expanded. Important chapters for risk assessment, such as &ldquo;Principles
				for prevention of the toxic effects of metals&rdquo;, &ldquo;Risk
				assessment&rdquo;
				and &ldquo;Essential
				metals: Assessing risks from deficiency and toxicity&rdquo;
				have been also expanded. The focus of the book is only on metals.
				From the view of feed science and animal nutrition, it would be
				favorable to expand the handbook to also include the toxicological
				effects of some non-metal elements such as phosphorus, sulfur,
				fluorine, iodine and further rare earth elements (not only
				lanthanum).
			</ce:para>
			<ce:para id="par0025">The editors of the book have for many years been
				involved in research with metals. Gunnar F. Nordberg is Professor
				Emeritus at the Department of Public Health and Clinical Medicine of
				the Umea University, Sweden; Bruce A. Fowler works as Adjunct
				Professor at the Rollins School of Public Health, Emory University,
				Atlanta, GA, and the Center for Alaska Native Health Research,
				University of Alaska Fairbanks, Fairbanks, AK, USA, and Monica
				Nordberg is Professor Emerita at the Institute of Environmental
				Medicine, Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden. Ninety-six
				colleagues from 16 countries supported the editors as chapter
				authors. Seventy scientists worked as chapter reviewers and
				contributed to the high scientific standard of the book.</ce:para>
			<ce:para id="par0030">
				All chapters are characterized by a similar structure. The General
				Considerations in the first volume (545 p.) describe some principles
				of Toxicology of metals: (1); Sampling. Analytical methods and
				speciation as general chemistry (2); Routes of exposure, dose and
				toxicokinetics of metals (3); Toxicity of metals and metal oxide
				nanoparticles (4); Toxicity of metals released from implanted
				medical devices (5); Toxic metals in food with subchapters for
				Cadmium, Lead, Mercury, Arsenic and food contamination from
				packaging (
				<ce:italic>e.g.</ce:italic>,
				Tin, Aluminum, Silver nanoparticles and Nickel (6); Exposure
				assessment, forward and reverse dosimetry (7); Biological monitoring
				and biomarkers including reference values (8); Selected molecular
				mechanisms of metal toxicity and carcinogenicity (9); General
				considerations of dose&ndash;effect
				and dose&ndash;response
				relationships (10); Interactions and mixtures in metal toxicology
				(11); Gene&ndash;environmental
				interactions for metals (12); Epidemiological approaches to metal
				toxicology (13); Essential metals: Assessing risks from deficiency
				and toxicology (14); Neurotoxicology of metals (15); Cardiovascular
				disease (16); Renal effects of exposure to metals (17);
				Carcinogenicity of metal compounds (18); Immunotoxicology of metals
				(19); Effects of metallic elements on reproduction and development
				(20); Risk assessment (22); Diagnosis and treatment of metal
				poisoning: General aspects (23); Principles for prevention of the
				toxic effects of metals (24) and Metal toxicology in developing
				countries (25). The length of the chapters in Volume I varies
				between 10 and 38 pages.
			</ce:para>
			<ce:para id="par0035">Volume II deals with specific metals in 31
				chapters on 836 pages. The metals are described in alphabetical
				order, beginning with Aluminum (26); followed by Antimony (27);
				Arsenic (28); Barium (29); Beryllium (30); Bismuth (31); Cadmium
				(32); Chromium (33); Cobalt (34); Copper (35); Gallium and Gallium
				semiconductor compounds (36); Germanium (37); Gold and Gold mining
				(38); Indium (39); Iridium (40); Iron (41); Lanthanum (42); Lead
				(43); Lithium (44); Manganese (45); Mercury (46); Molybdenum (47);
				Nickel (48); Palladium (49); Platinum (50); Rhodium (51); Selenium
				(52); Silver (53); Tellurium (54); Thallium (55); Tin (56) Titanium
				(57); Tungsten (58); Uranium (59); Vanadium (60) and Zinc (61). The
				length of the chapters in Volume II varies between 7 (Lanthanum) and
				63 (Mercury) pages.</ce:para>
			<ce:para id="par0040">There
				is an Index (31 pages) at the end both volumes. The book offers a
				complete review on general aspects on metals, such as physical and
				chemical properties, analytical methods, production and uses,
				toxicology, environmental levels and exposures, metabolism, levels
				in tissues and biological fluids, effects of dose&ndash;response
				relationships and many other topics.
			</ce:para>
			<ce:para id="par0045">The &ldquo;Handbook
				on the Toxicology of Metals&rdquo;
				is an excellent tool for MSc and PhD students in various fields of
				natural sciences, scientists in chemical laboratories and in
				general, for all those working with metals, also in feed and animal
				production and in feed and food safety.
			</ce:para>
		</ce:sections>
	</body>
</book-review>